<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sermon of Henry Walker, ironmonger: having beene twice apprehended, for writing seditious pamphlets. Being both times rescued out of the hands of the officers. And now preacheth up and downe the City.</title>
            <author>Walker, Henry, Ironmonger.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E141_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212741</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871317</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871317</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 25:E141[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sermon of Henry Walker, ironmonger: having beene twice apprehended, for writing seditious pamphlets. Being both times rescued out of the hands of the officers. And now preacheth up and downe the City.</title>
                  <author>Walker, Henry, Ironmonger.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for I.C.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walker, Henry, --  Ironmonger --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XIII, 24 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156561:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Sermon of HENRY WALKER, IRONMONGER: Having beene twice Apprehended, for Writing ſeditious Pamphlets.</p>
            <p>Being both times reſcued out of the Hands of the Officers.</p>
            <p>And now preacheth up and downe the City.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matthew, cap. 7. ver. 13.14.</bibl>
               <p>Enter yee in at the ſtrait Gate, for wide is the Gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be which goe in thereat.</p>
               <p>Becauſe ſtrait is the Gate, and narrow is the Way which leadeth unto life, and few there be that finde it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for I. <hi>C.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:156561:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156561:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Luk. 13.24.</bibl>
                  <p>Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate: for many, I ſay unto you, will ſeeke to enter in, and ſhall not be able.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>THe Queſtion formerly examined, being conceived (as by ſome of judgement it is) to be not onely needleſſely cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, but alſo impiouſly carping, and captious; herein, as in a cleare mirror, we may behold diſcovered the humours that have ever been in all ages amongſt the people of the World; and in ſpeciall how, <hi>This great and higheſt point of truth, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the matter and means of ſalvation, is entertained, eith with carping impiety, or with dangerous curioſity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For ſo, to ſhew that this caviller, and his queſtion, be not without fellowes as it is moſt certain, that no elder age of the World hath wanted them, who, in the pride of their rebellious and unbelieving hearts, have been bold to make a mocke, and to move cavill againſt the Sacred truth of God, in his Word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, which eaſily might be inſtanced, even from the daies of <hi>Adam,</hi> downward untill Chriſt: ſo, that we may not thinke ſuch cavillers, by Chriſts comming, to be together with the Heathen Oracles, quite put to ſilence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath not ſpared to forewarne us of the <hi>comming in the laſt dayes of ſuch mockers; who walking after their own luſts, ſhall aske, where is the promiſe of the comming,</hi> and be ready to bring reaſon againſt it, as if there were no ſuch matter to be looked for.</p>
               <p>And accordingly, how eaſie, alas, is it, now adaies, to finde, and that amongſt ſuch as profeſſe themſelves worſhippers of the true God in Chriſt, many every where of captious, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting ſpirits; who not onely live the life, but ſpeak alſo the very
<pb facs="tcp:156561:3"/> language of Atheiſme, bewraying by rheir tongues, their ſpite, and deepe diſlike againſt the truth of Chriſt, revealed in his Word; ſpecially in this very point of points, touching Mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Who if they be called upon, according to the tenour of the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Doctrine, <hi>to repent, and beleeve the Goſpel, to walke circumſpectly,</hi> as by a line, <hi>abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the faſhions</hi> and courſes <hi>of this preſent World, and taking heed unto their waies, according to the Word,</hi> that ſo they may be ſaved: what ſhall you heare from them ſtreight, but queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and reaſonings, ſuch as this in our Text, uttering the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe of their ignorantly prophane hearts?</p>
               <p>For (to give inſtance in ſome few of their curſed ſpeakings) <q>Then belike, <hi>will they reply,</hi> there can none be ſaved but ſuch as follow Sermons, which commonly are not the moſt, and ſome of them as bad, as proud, covetous, and malicious, as any whoſoever. <hi>Or,</hi> what? if none can be ſaued, but ſuch as will be ſo pure forſooth, and holy, as your Preachers would have them; then God be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto us, for ſure, but a few of many ſhould be ſaved. And then; <hi>What then? why?</hi> By this reckoning, you would make God not to be ſo ſtrong, as the Devill: <hi>Or,</hi> how can that be true, that God would have all men ſaved? <hi>For,</hi> though we be ſinners, yet, did not Chriſt die for all? <hi>Or,</hi> Is not God mercifull, yea, his mercy above all his works? <hi>Or,</hi> may we thinke that God made ſo many to condemne them? Yea, and what? Predeſtinated them of old unto it ere they were borne? Indeed, <hi>ſaith the Papiſticall Atheiſt,</hi> Sir, I have heard Preachers preach of Predeſtination; but me thinks, it is a very dangerous Doctrine, able to drive men to deſpaire. <hi>Or,</hi> What? can they tell who ſhall be ſaved, and who ſhall be damned? Doe they know Gods ſecrets? When, I marvell, were they in Heaven to ſpeak with God? <hi>Or,</hi> be not they men as well as others? And good, many of them, no longer then whiles they are in the Pulpit? Well, we be ſinners all, God amend us; and then we ſhall, I doubt not, all at length come to Heaven.</q>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:156561:3"/>
               <p>I appeale herein, to the judgement of ſo many, as are able to diſcerne, and have had experience of any thing; whether theſe be not the queſtions and reaſonings, touching this maine point of ſalvation and damnation, of many of all ſorts, no better herein then very Atheiſts, who believing neither God, nor his revealed Truth, would faine flatter themſelves in a vaine delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hope; that, <q>Live how they liſt, <hi>and</hi> doe what they pleaſe; <hi>Yet</hi> God is mercifull; and whenſoever a ſinner ſhall repent, &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> Chriſt dyed for all, <hi>and ſo for them; and therefore,</hi> they doubt nothing but they ſhall be ſaved, as ſoon as the beſt. <hi>Or,</hi> ſay, they be bad, yet they be not the worſt in the World, there be as bad as they; <hi>and,</hi> if the worſt thereof befall them, that they doe goe to Hell, yet they ſhall have fellowes, and truſt to make as good ſhift for themſelves, as ſhall ſome others.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But, (to leave theſe wretches, and their humours for a while may we not note alſo another ſort, not ſo impious, but of a more indifferent temper; who yet through idle <hi>curioſity,</hi> are dangerouſly tranſported, from embracing the means and way of ſalvation preſcribed to make queſtion how many, or what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhall be ſaved? Yes verily; but who herein ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be, what Saint <hi>Peter</hi> would not have Chriſtians to be, <hi>buſie bodies</hi> or (or as the word originally importeth) as <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in anothers Dioceſſe.</hi> As yet once, the ſame Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſeeme to have been, when our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaying to him, <hi>Follow me;</hi> He replyed ſtreight upon the ſight of <hi>Iohn</hi> with, Lord, <hi>what ſhall this man doe?</hi> Right like to whom in humour, may the moſt part of men be found, more curious in enquiring what they need not, whether, or how many others ſhall be ſaved; then faithfully carefull, to do what God requireth, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may atttain ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Nay herein how many are there, that agree in humour, with that <hi>Perſian Prince;</hi> who when by the French men, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:156561:4"/> government of <hi>Charles Martell,</hi> about the yeare of Chriſt, 730. the <hi>Phryſians</hi> were compelled to embrace the Chriſtian faith, coming to be baptiſed, and having one foot in the water is recorded to have turned about to the Biſhop, deſiring, firſt, to be reſolved, whether more, already departed, were in hell, or more in heaven; but receiving anſwer, that the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were in hell, whither all muſt that would not be baptiſed, and become Chriſtians, refuſed thereupon to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, pulling his foot, out of the water, and profeſſing that he would follow where the moſt were gone before.</p>
               <p>This you will perhaps ſay, was the deſperate humour of an Infidell, that knew not God: Howbeit, would God he had not left behind him, even amongſt Chriſtians, many his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, all too kinde hearted; good fellowes in this behalf; who though in words they will not for ſhame profeſſe, yet prove by their licentious life, and wicked deeds, that they had rather with the multitude, though wandring along to hell, then with the leſſer, but far wiſer company, to go ſtreight to heaven, curiouſly enquiring, as here this companion, touching the number of them thall be ſaved, how great or ſmall it is; wiſhing in heart, and hoping it will be great, that ſo they might ſhuffle in, amongſt the multitude; but not caring truly to learne, or when they are directed, obediently to follow, and walk in that path, which will, though it be narrow, lead them unto life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond main part: our Saviours <hi>Anſwer:</hi> And <hi>firſt</hi> what is—<hi>implyed</hi> that <hi>but few, are to be ſaved.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe bad <hi>Humours</hi> of the world mentioned, and in part met withall, being hereafter farther to be cenſured; we may paſſe, from the conſideration of the <hi>Queſtion</hi> and proceed to the <hi>Anſwer,</hi> which our bleſſed Saviour, his Fathers wiſedome, hath
<pb facs="tcp:156561:4"/> wiſely, and to better puppoſe, framed, for direction, and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up of ſo many, as ſeriouſly deſire no enter into life: <hi>Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, for many, I ſay to you, will ſeeke to enter in and ſhall not be able.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherein we have two things to obſerve in generall: Firſt, is implyed. <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Reſolution</hi> of the queſtion mooved touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>number</hi> of them that ſhall be ſaved. Secondly what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <hi>viz.</hi> an <hi>Exhortation,</hi> or counſell together with a reaſon to enforce it, touching the <hi>manner</hi> of attaining unto ſalvation.</p>
               <p>And firſt for the implying <hi>Reſolution</hi> of the queſtion, we may conceive our Saviour dealing here with this queſtioning companion, right, as <hi>Solomon</hi> directeth a wiſe man to deale with a foole; whiles he <hi>anſwereth him not, according to his fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> that is, not directly to his queſtion as he expected, leſt ſo he might ſeem to approve it as a queſtion pertinent, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden him to further reply: and yet, <hi>according to his fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he anſwereth him,</hi> that is, howſoever indirectly, yet fully to the point, that he might not grow wiſe, as ſuch Cock-brains will, if they be let alone, unanſwered in) his own conceit. For why? whiles here he giveth warning, borh to him, and all the reſt, <hi>to ſtrive</hi> and ſtruggle and even ſweat and wreſtle as thoſe do that <hi>try Maſteries</hi> (for from ſuch violence is the word here bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed) <hi>to enter in,</hi> viz. into Heaven, by <hi>the ſtrait and narrow gate,</hi> as the onely doore to life, telling them, the more to ſtirre them up to care, that <hi>Many will ſeek to enter,</hi> if wiſhing, and willing would ſerve, who yet for want of earneſt violenec, <hi>ſhall be ſhut out:</hi> how doth he not onely imply an anſwer to the queſtion moved, that indeed, but a few, in compariſon with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſhall be ſaved; but alſo to prevent all farther cavilling, yield withall a reaſon, to the ſtraitneſſe of the gate, whereat therefore ſo many ſticke, why it it is ſo few come to be ſaved.</p>
               <p>From which reſolution of the point, that which it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:156561:5"/> our Saviour to reveal, we may be bold for our inſtruction to take notice of, touching the counſell of Gods will in this particular, namely, that:—<hi>They are but few, the leſſer number of mankinde, that ſhall enter into heaven and be ſaved.</hi>—For what in this anſwer Chriſt implyeth, we may ſee how elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, he more fully openeth, making as it were, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon this Text, in <hi>Math.</hi> 7.13.14. <hi>Enter in at the ſtrait gate: For it is the wide gate, and broad way, that leadeth to deſtruction: and many there be that go in thereat: Becauſe the gate is ſtrait, and the way narrow that leadeth unto life, and few there be that finde it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
